  <chapter>
      <title>Working with Requirements</title>
    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Project Navigation</title>
      </info>

      <para>Figure 9 shows a close up of the project navigation tab with the
      &quot;Purchase Order System&quot; project node in a closed state and the &quot;Requel&quot;
      project node in an open state. Clicking on the project name opens the
      &quot;Project Overview&quot; panel for editing the name, description and
      organization of the project, as well as adding issues and notes to the
      project. Clicking on the + next to a project name in the project
      navigation tab expands the project node to display the links to the
      requirements elements.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="206.25pt" fileref="0300000B.png" width="162pt" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Creating and Editing Stakeholders</title>
      </info>

      <para>The first task to do after creating a new project is adding
      stakeholders for the users that will work on the project. Clicking on
      the &quot;Stakeholders&quot; link under a project in the navigation tab opens the
      stakeholder navigator, which lists all the stakeholders on the project,
      ordered by username as shown in Figure 10.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="194.25pt" fileref="0300000C.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Users authorized to edit stakeholders will see an &quot;Edit&quot; link in
      the first column of each stakeholder entry in the table and an &quot;Add&quot;
      button below the table. If you are not authorized to edit stakeholders
      the first column contains a &quot;View&quot; link that opens the stakeholder
      editor, but with read-only access. Clicking on the column titles sorts
      the stakeholders by that column. The first click sorts them in ascending
      order alphabetically as shown in Figure 11.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="133.5pt" fileref="0300000D.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The column indicates the sorting order with an arrow next to the
      column name. An arrow pointing up indicates ascending order and an arrow
      pointing down indicates descending order. Clicking on the column title,
      when it is sorted in ascending order, changes the sorting to descending
      order. Note: stakeholders without a name, for example the admin and
      project stakeholders in Figure 11, appear at the end of the
      results.</para>

      <para>There will always be at least two stakeholders, the person that
      created the project and the &quot;Analysis Assistant&quot; that the system uses to
      indicate issues and notes created by the system.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="205.5pt" fileref="0300000E.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button on the stakeholder navigator screen
      opens the &quot;New Stakeholder&quot; screen shown in Figure 12. This screen is
      used for creating both user and non-user stakeholders for the project.
      To create a user stakeholder, leave the &quot;Non-User Name&quot; field empty and
      select a user from the &quot;User&quot; field, as shown in Figure 13.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="133.5pt" fileref="0300000F.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Only administrators can create user accounts. If a person that you
      want to add to a project doesn’t appear in the list they may not have a
      user account. You should ask the Requel administrator to add an account
      for that person, with the &quot;Project User&quot; role.</para>

      <para>You may optionally enter or select a team name in the &quot;Team&quot;
      field. The team is for documentation purposes only. Customer and
      Supplier are examples of team names.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="141.75pt" fileref="03000010.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>User stakeholders can view all requirements elements on a project,
      but require explicit authorization to edit or delete requirements. The
      &quot;Stakeholder Permissions&quot; field contains a tree with nodes for each of
      the requirement element types. Each of the nodes has child nodes with
      permissions for actions such as &quot;Delete&quot;, &quot;Edit&quot;, and &quot;Grant&quot;, and a
      checkbox as shown in Figure 14. Checking a box grants permission to the
      user to perform that action on that element type; unchecking the box
      revokes the permission. For example in Figure 14 the checkbox for &quot;Edit&quot;
      under &quot;Actor&quot; is checked indicating the user can create and edit
      actors.</para>

      <para>The &quot;Grant&quot; action permission allows a user with stakeholder
      &quot;Edit&quot; permission to grant permissions for that element type to other
      users. For example, if stakeholder &quot;A&quot; has stakeholder edit permission
      and story grant permission, he or she can edit stakeholder &quot;B&quot; and grant
      or revoke &quot;Delete&quot;, &quot;Edit&quot;, and &quot;Grant&quot; permission for actors to
      stakeholder &quot;B&quot;. If stakeholder &quot;A&quot; does not have grant permission for
      story elements, he or she can not grant or revoke permissions related to
      stories to stakeholder &quot;B.&quot;</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="170.25pt" fileref="03000011.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Non-user stakeholders represent organizations or regulatory bodies
      that don’t have a user representative, but have interests or goals that
      the system must meet. Figure 15 shows a non-user stakeholder &quot;Harvard
      University&quot; with one goal named &quot;Work is your own&quot;; representing that
      projects submitted for homework are expected to be your own work.
      Non-user stakeholders are created using the same screen as user
      stakeholders, but instead of selecting a user, a name is entered in the
      &quot;Non-User Name&quot; field. Non-user stakeholders may have a team.
      Stakeholder permissions don’t make sense for non-user
      stakeholders.</para>

      <para>After creating a stakeholder, goals can be added to it. Both user
      and non-user stakeholders can have goals. A new goal can be added by
      clicking the &quot;New&quot; button, which opens the &quot;New Goal&quot; screen, or an
      existing goal can be added to the stakeholder by clicking the &quot;Find&quot;
      button and selecting a goal from the goal selector panel. Figure 16
      shows the goal selector panel with the selected goal highlighted.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="204.75pt" fileref="03000012.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The full goal can be viewed or edited by clicking on the &quot;Edit&quot;
      link in the first column of the goal table. The goal can be removed from
      the stakeholder by clicking the &quot;Remove&quot; link as shown in Figure 15.
      Removing a goal from a stakeholder does not delete it from the
      system.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Creating and Editing Goals</title>
      </info>

      <para>Goals are used to indicate desired properties, qualities,
      constraints, features and functions that the system must support. For
      example, &quot;Easy to Use&quot; is a high-level quality goal; &quot;Must run on Linux&quot;
      is a technology constraint; &quot;Support an IBIS style of discussion&quot; is a
      feature.</para>

      <para>Clicking on the &quot;Goals&quot; link in the project navigation tab opens
      the goal navigator screen shown in Figure 17. The goal navigator has a
      table with the name of each goal, who created it, and when it was
      created. If you are authorized to edit goals the first column contains
      an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table is an &quot;Add&quot; button. If you are not
      authorized to edit goals the first column contains a &quot;View&quot; link that
      opens the goal editor for read-only viewing.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="192pt" fileref="03000013.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the add button opens the &quot;New Goal&quot; screen shown in
      Figure 18. Goals have a name, which is a short one-line description, and
      a text body that is the full description of the goal. The goal name must
      be unique in a project. After entering a name and text body, click the
      save button at the bottom of the screen to create the goal. If the name
      is unique the system creates the goal and adds it to the goal navigator
      table.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="192pt" fileref="03000014.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If the goal was created from another requirements element such as
      a stakeholder or use case, then the goal is also added to the goals
      field of that element. All the entities that refer to a goal are shown
      in the goal editor’s &quot;Referring Entities&quot; table shown in Figure
      19.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="91.5pt" fileref="03000015.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Upon saving the goal, the system initiates analysis of the goal as
      a background task referred to as the &quot;Automated Assistant.&quot; The
      assistant adds notes and issues to the goal as it analyzes it. During
      analysis of a goal the assistant identifies unknown or misspelled words;
      potential &quot;significant terms&quot; to add to the glossary; potential actors
      that don’t already exist in the project; and complex sentences that may
      be difficult to understand. You may work on any requirements elements as
      the assistant analyzes them; the assistant will not interfere with your
      work. See the Working with Analysis Issues section for more information
      about the analysis.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="86.25pt" fileref="03000016.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Goals can have relationships with other goals listed in the goal
      editor’s &quot;Relations to Other Goals&quot; field, as shown in Figure 20. The
      relationships can be used to add traceability of goals from high level
      soft goals to specific functional requirements and as an indication of
      how goals interact with each other. Goals may support or conflict with
      each other. Conflicts help to identify places where tradeoffs may be
      needed, and to document the rationale behind the decisions made. Goal
      relations are directional, for example if goal &quot;A&quot; supports goal &quot;B&quot;
      there is a relationship from goal &quot;A&quot; to goal &quot;B&quot;, but not from goal &quot;B&quot;
      to goal &quot;A&quot;.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="186pt" fileref="03000017.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button opens the &quot;New Goal Relation&quot; editor as
      shown in Figure 21. A goal relation has a &quot;From Goal&quot;, a &quot;To Goal&quot;, and
      the relation type. The editor defaults the &quot;From Goal&quot; selector to the
      goal in the editor where the add button was clicked. Both the &quot;To&quot; and
      &quot;From&quot; goal fields list all the goals in the project as possible options
      as shown in Figure 22. After selecting the &quot;To Goal&quot; and relation type,
      clicking save creates the relationship and adds it to the goal relations
      table of the original goal as shown in Figure 20.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="193.5pt" fileref="03000018.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Creating and Editing Stories</title>
      </info>

      <para>Stories are simple narratives of how a user interacts with the
      system. Stories can be used to describe how things work before the new
      system is in place, i.e. the current state of affairs, or how things
      will be when the new system is in place. Stories can describe negative
      cases, such as problems with the current system, or how the new system
      should behave in a bad situation.</para>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Stories&quot; link in the project navigator tab opens the
      stories navigation screen as shown in Figure 23.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="186pt" fileref="03000019.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The stories navigator has a table with the name, type, who created
      it, and when it was created. If you are authorized to edit stories the
      first column contains an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table is an &quot;Add&quot;
      button. If you are not authorized to edit stories the first column
      contains a &quot;View&quot; link that opens the story editor in read-only
      mode.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="186.75pt" fileref="0300001A.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Edit&quot; button for an existing story opens the story
      editor screen shown in Figure 24. A story has a short one-line name, a
      type of &quot;Success&quot; or &quot;Exception&quot; and a text body. The story name must be
      unique in the project. Clicking the &quot;Save&quot; button, located at the bottom
      of the screen, validates and creates or updates the story and initiates
      analysis as a background task. See the Working with Analysis Issues
      section for more information about the analysis.</para>

      <para>Optionally, stories can have goals and actors assigned. The actors
      add traceability to the types of users appropriate to the story. The
      goals can be used to indicate the goals supported by the story or
      derived from the story. For both goals and actors there are &quot;New&quot; and
      &quot;Find&quot; buttons as shown in Figure 25. The &quot;New&quot; button is used to open
      an editor for creating a new actor or goal that gets assigned to the
      story. The &quot;Find&quot; button is used to open a selector, like the one in
      Figure 16, to choose an existing goal or actor.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="170.25pt" fileref="0300001B.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Creating and Editing Actors</title>
      </info>

      <para>Actors represent the types of users that will interact with the
      system. Actors may be human users or other systems. Clicking on the
      &quot;Actors&quot; link in the project navigation tab opens the actor navigator
      screen shown in Figure 26. The actor navigator contains a table of the
      actors with columns for the name, description, who created it, and when
      it was created. If you are authorized to edit actors the first column
      contains an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table is an &quot;Add&quot; button. If you
      are not authorized to edit actors the first column contains a &quot;View&quot;
      link that opens the actor editor for read-only viewing.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="171.75pt" fileref="0300001C.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button opens the &quot;New Actor&quot; editor as shown in
      Figure 27.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="177pt" fileref="0300001D.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>An actor has a name that must be unique in the project, and a
      description. The description can be used to describe the actor’s primary
      function or to describe an example &quot;persona&quot; for a person or system that
      typifies the actor. For example the following is a persona for a user of
      the Requel system:</para>

      <blockquote>
        <para>Theresa is an accountant for Bailey Pet Supply tasked with
        specifying the requirements for integrating the purchase order system
        with the accounting system using the system. Theresa has never used a
        requirements tool before and has no projects. Theresa will be an
        end-user of the resulting system.</para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>Actors may have goals that identify the functions of the system
      relevant to the actor, or general interests that the actor has that the
      system must meet. Figure 28 shows the goal references of an actor in the
      Requel system.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="130.5pt" fileref="0300001E.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>From the actor editor new goals can be added using the &quot;New&quot;
      button or existing goals can be added using the &quot;Find&quot; button. Goals
      attached to the actor can be removed by clicking the &quot;Remove&quot; link in
      the first column of the goals table. Goals that are removed from the
      actor are not deleted from the project.</para>

      <para>Like other requirements element actors are analyzed when saved.
      See the Working with Analysis Issues section for more information about
      the analysis.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Creating and Editing Scenarios</title>
      </info>

      <para>Scenarios are semi-structured sequences of steps where the actor
      invokes an action on the system in one step, followed by a response by
      the system in the next step. Scenarios are composed of an ordered list
      of steps where a step may be a single action or a reference to another
      scenario with its own set of steps. Scenarios may be used as stand alone
      entities that describe an interaction more explicitly than a story, or
      in conjunction with a use case.</para>

      <para>Clicking on the &quot;Scenarios&quot; link in the project navigator opens
      the scenarios navigator screen as shown in Figure 29. In addition to the
      standard name, created by, and date created columns, the scenario
      navigator has two additional columns: &quot;Top Level&quot; and &quot;Type&quot;. The top
      level column indicates if a scenario is used as a step in another
      scenario. Scenarios with a &quot;Yes&quot; value means the scenario is a top level
      scenario and not used in other scenarios. The type column indicates how
      the scenario is used, for example if it is used as an alternate,
      exceptional, or optional sequence of steps in another scenario.</para>

      <para>If you are authorized to edit scenarios the first column contains
      an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table is an &quot;Add&quot; button. If you are not
      authorized to edit scenarios the first column contains a &quot;View&quot; link
      that opens the scenario editor for read-only viewing.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="185.25pt" fileref="0300001F.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button opens the &quot;New Scenario&quot; editor as shown
      in Figure 30. A scenario has a name, type, optional descriptive text,
      and a sequence of steps. The scenario name must be unique in a project.
      The type of scenario is most relevant for scenarios that are steps in
      other scenarios and is described in the Editing Scenario Steps section,
      which gives a description of how to add and edit the steps of a
      scenario.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="161.25pt" fileref="03000020.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The scenario editor lists the scenarios that use the scenario
      being edited in the &quot;Referring Scenarios&quot; table as shown in Figure 31.
      Clicking the edit link in the table opens the scenario editor for that
      scenario.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="80.25pt" fileref="03000021.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Creating and Editing Use Cases</title>
      </info>

      <para>Use cases represent functional requirements in terms of how a user
      interacts with the system. In the Requel system a use case is a
      confluence of stories, goals, and actors with a scenario to describe the
      behavior of a specific function of the system.</para>

      <para>Clicking on the &quot;Use Cases&quot; link in the project navigator opens
      the use case navigator screen as shown in Figure 32. The navigator
      includes columns for the use case name, primary actor, created by
      username, and date created. If you are authorized to edit use cases the
      first column contains an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table is an &quot;Add&quot;
      button. If you are not authorized to edit use cases the first column
      contains a &quot;View&quot; link that opens the use case editor for read-only
      viewing.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="175.5pt" fileref="03000022.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button opens the &quot;New Use Case&quot; editor as shown
      in Figure 33. A use case has a name, which must be unique in a project,
      an optional description, and a primary actor. The primary actor input is
      a combo-box where the actor can be selected from the drop-down list, or
      a name can be entered. If a name is entered, when the use case is saved,
      a new actor is created, added to the project, and set as the primary
      actor. The description and other information of the actor can be edited
      later, by opening the actor editor through the actor navigation
      screen.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="175.5pt" fileref="03000023.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A use case can contain a set of goals that represent what the
      primary actor is trying to accomplish with the use case. Goals are added
      and removed from use cases just like goals on other entities, such as on
      the actor editor screen as shown in Figure 28.</para>

      <para>Most use cases only have a single primary actor, but in some cases
      additional actors are needed to show complex interactions where the
      system interacts with external services to support the user’s actions.
      Auxiliary actors are displayed in a table as shown in Figure 34. Like
      goals, a new actor can be created and added, or an existing actor can be
      added to the auxiliary actors of the use case.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="84pt" fileref="03000024.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Use cases can reference multiple stories as example of successful
      and exceptional interactions with the system. Stories are useful as
      rationale for understanding the scenario of the use case. Stories are
      displayed in a table as shown in Figure 35 and can be added and removed
      just like actors and goals.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="90.75pt" fileref="03000025.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Editing the scenario of the use case is described in the Editing
      Scenario Steps section.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Editing Scenario Steps</title>
      </info>

      <para>The scenario step editor is used by both the scenario editor and
      use case editor screens. When creating a new scenario the steps editor
      appears with no steps and two buttons as shown in Figure 36.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="70.5pt" fileref="03000026.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The &quot;Add Step&quot; button creates an empty step node as shown in
      Figure 37. New steps are added below any existing steps.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="30pt" fileref="03000027.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="column-1" colwidth="1260*" />

          <colspec colname="column-2" colwidth="5940*" />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <figure>
                  <info />

                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata depth="29.25pt" fileref="03000028.png"
                                 width="36.75pt" />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The &quot;slotted puzzle&quot; icon is used to drag a step to a
                new location in the scenario by dropping it on the tabbed
                puzzle piece. A step can be dragged from and dropped to any
                sub-step level.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <figure>
                  <info />

                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata depth="34.5pt" fileref="03000029.png"
                                 width="36pt" />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The &quot;tabbed puzzle&quot; icon is the drop target for moving a
                step. Dropping a step on the target inserts that step in the
                location and moves the existing all subsequent steps down by
                one.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <figure>
                  <info />

                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata depth="27.75pt" fileref="0300002A.png"
                                 width="27.75pt" />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The &quot;X&quot; button removes the step from the scenario and
                moves all subsequent steps up by one. If the step is a simple
                step with no sub-steps it is deleted from the project. If the
                step is a sub-scenario it is removed, but not deleted.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <figure>
                  <info />

                  <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata depth="27pt" fileref="0300002B.png"
                                 width="27pt" />
                    </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </figure>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The &quot;sub-step&quot; button adds a new sub-step to this step.
                If the step has other sub-steps the new one is added at the
                end of the sequence.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>

        <caption>
          <para>Table 1: Step Node Controls</para>
        </caption>
      </informaltable>

      <para>Sub-steps can be nested to any level. Each step that contains
      sub-steps has a &quot;-&quot; button to the left of all other controls when the
      sub-steps are visible. Clicking it hides the sub-steps. When a step’s
      sub-steps are hidden the step has a &quot;+&quot; button, which exposes the
      sub-steps when clicked.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Generating Documents</title>
      </info>

      <para>Once the requirements are in Requel you will want to generate a
      specification document to provide to the developers to build the system.
      Just as there are many processes for acquiring requirements, there are
      many formats for specifying requirements. Requel supports creating
      custom documentation using the XML Stylesheet Language Transformations
      (XSLT) language to transform the requirements from an XML format into a
      specification document. XSLT is a powerful language that can transform
      XML into a variety of structured or unstructured document formats such
      as HTML, PDF, and Microsoft Office documents using the Office Open XML
      format.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="175.5pt" fileref="0300002E.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking on the &quot;Documents&quot; link in the project navigation opens
      the documents navigator as shown in Figure 40. Each entry in the table
      represents an XSLT script for generating a document. If you are
      authorized to edit documents (in the stakeholder permissions it is
      labeled as ReportGenerator) the first column contains an &quot;Edit&quot; link and
      below the table is an &quot;Add&quot; button. If you are not authorized to edit
      documents the first column contains a &quot;View&quot; link that opens the
      document editor for read-only viewing.</para>

      <para>The second column of the table holds a &quot;Run&quot; link that executes
      the XSLT script on the requirements to generate a document. The document
      is returned to the browser, which gives you the option to open it or
      save it as shown in Figure 41. The document will have the project’s name
      as the file name with an appropriate extension for the type of document
      as a suffix. For example, an HTML document for a project named &quot;Requel&quot;
      will be named &quot;Requel.html&quot;.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="175.5pt" fileref="0300002F.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The built-in &quot;HTML Specification&quot; document is added to all
      projects when they are created. It generates a simply formatted Web page
      with all requirements elements as shown in Figure 42. There is a section
      for each of the requirement element types: stakeholders, actors, goals,
      stories, use cases and scenarios. At the top of the document is a table
      of contents that links to each section and also to each element of the
      requirements.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="216.75pt" fileref="03000030.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Adding a Document Generator</title>
      </info>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button opens the &quot;New Document&quot; editor as shown
      in Figure 43. A document has a name, which must be unique in the
      project, and the XSLT script text.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="186pt" fileref="03000031.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>An XSLT can be uploaded from your local system by clicking the
      &quot;Browse&quot; button, finding the file with the file upload dialog, and then
      clicking the &quot;Upload&quot; button. The contents of the XSLT will be loaded in
      the &quot;Text&quot; field. You can edit the XSLT in the text box, but it is not
      an effective tool for more than simple text changes.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Working with Terms</title>
      </info>

      <para>Each project has a glossary of terms. Using a glossary to
      explicitly define how words are used in a project can help improve
      understanding by using a consistent and explicitly defined set of terms.
      Clicking on the &quot;Terms&quot; link in the project navigator opens the terms
      navigator screen shown in Figure 44. If you are authorized to edit terms
      (in the stakeholder permissions it is labeled as GlossaryTerm) the first
      column contains an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table is an &quot;Add&quot; button.
      If you are not authorized to edit terms the first column contains a
      &quot;View&quot; link that opens the term editor for read-only viewing.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="177pt" fileref="03000032.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The terms navigator shows the text of the term in the &quot;Name&quot;
      column and the full text of the definition. The canonical term column
      contains the name of another term if the term is not the preferred term
      for the concept. For example the term &quot;the application&quot; in Figure 45 has
      the term &quot;The system&quot; as the canonical term. Ideally there should only
      be one term per concept and the system has a feature to solve this
      problem described below.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="16.5pt" fileref="03000033.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking the &quot;Edit&quot; button on a term opens the term editor shown
      in Figure 46. The editor has text fields for the name and description
      and a selector button for choosing a canonical term.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="178.5pt" fileref="03000034.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The selector button displays &quot;&lt;nothing selected&gt;&quot; when the
      term doesn’t have a canonical term. Clicking the &quot;Select&quot; button opens a
      selector screen that looks like the navigator screen. When a canonical
      term is selected the name of the term shows up to the left of the button
      as shown in Figure 47. When creating a new term or changing the name of
      the term, the system scans all the requirements and adds
      cross-references between the elements and the term.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="36.75pt" fileref="03000035.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>As stated before, ideally there should only be one term per
      concept. In many cases different people use different terms to refer to
      the same thing when writing requirements individually. To solve the
      problem Requel has function that will replace all the occurrences of a
      term with its canonical term in all the requirement elements. First, all
      the terms need to be added to the glossary. The automated assistant will
      probably create issues identifying them as potential glossary terms;
      resolving these issues will create the terms and add references to all
      the requirement elements that use them. For all the terms that you want
      to replace, edit them and select the preferred term as the canonical
      term. At the bottom of the term editor is a &quot;Replace Term&quot; button shown
      in Figure 48. Clicking the button causes the system to update all the
      occurrences of the term in the requirements elements with its canonical
      term.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="42pt" fileref="03000036.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <info>
      <title>Discussing and Negotiating Requirements</title>
    </info>

    <para>This section describes adding notes and issues to requirements, and
    negotiating resolutions to issues.</para>

    <para>Discussion and negotiation are an important aspect of collaboration.
    For example a stakeholder adds an issue indicating a goal needs more
    details. Other stakeholders then propose solutions to the issue, and argue
    the merits of each with arguments supporting or conflicting with the
    potential solution. Once all the proposed solutions have been discussed,
    one can be chosen as the resolution.</para>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Adding Notes and Issues</title>
      </info>

      <para>All the requirements elements support adding notes and issues.
      Each of the requirements editors has an &quot;Annotations&quot; table with the
      notes and issues as shown in Figure 49. If you are authorized to edit
      annotations the first column contains an &quot;Edit&quot; link and below the table
      are &quot;Add Issue&quot; and &quot;Add Note&quot; buttons. If you are not authorized to
      edit annotations the first column contains a &quot;View&quot; link that opens the
      note or issue editor for read-only viewing. Note: typically you will
      want all stakeholders to have &quot;Edit&quot; permission for annotations.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="180pt" fileref="03000037.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The type column in the table indicates if the annotation is a note
      or issue. The status column will always have the value &quot;Informational&quot;
      for notes and either &quot;Unresolved&quot; or &quot;Resolution: …&quot; for issues. When an
      issue is resolved the status will start with &quot;Resolution:&quot; followed by
      the text of the position that resolved the issue. The &quot;Must be
      Resolved?&quot; column will always have &quot;No&quot; for notes and either &quot;Yes&quot; or
      &quot;No&quot; for issues. The &quot;Text&quot; column contains the full text of the
      issue.</para>

      <para>Clicking on the &quot;Add Note&quot; button opens the &quot;New Note&quot; editor as
      shown in Figure 50. A note only has the text of the note.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="178.5pt" fileref="03000038.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>There isn’t a way to find existing notes and add them to multiple
      requirement elements, but the system automatically detects adding notes
      with identical text and instead of creating a new note it will add the
      existing note to the requirement. Figure 51 shows a note shared by two
      goals, indicated in the &quot;Referring Entities&quot; table.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="217.5pt" fileref="03000039.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Clicking on the &quot;Add Issue&quot; button opens the &quot;New Issue&quot; editor as
      shown in Figure 52. An issue has text, a must be resolved checkbox, and
      positions. The must be resolved property is only for documentation
      purposes.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="178.5pt" fileref="0300003A.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After an issue is saved positions can be added by users authorized
      to edit issues by clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button below the positions table as
      shown in Figure 53.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="108pt" fileref="0300003B.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Positions represent potential solutions to an issue. The position
      editor has a text field to enter the text of the position and a table of
      arguments that argue for or against the position as a solution to the
      issue, as shown in Figure 54. After a position is saved arguments can be
      added by users authorized to edit issues by clicking the &quot;Add&quot; button
      below the arguments table.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="190.5pt" fileref="0300003C.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Arguments are the reasons why a particular position of an issue
      should or should not be chosen as the solution. Arguments have text
      description and a support level with values from &quot;strongly against&quot; to
      &quot;strongly for.&quot; Clicking the add or edit button opens the argument
      editor shown in Figure 55. The argument editor has a field for entering
      the text of the argument and a drop down list with the support
      levels.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="180.75pt" fileref="0300003D.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>All the open issues for all the elements of a project can be seen
      on the &quot;Open Issues&quot; screen as shown in Figure 56. The screen can be
      opened from the project navigator &quot;Open Issues&quot; link. The issues screen
      has a &quot;View&quot; link for each issue that opens the issue editor. The issues
      table has a column labeled &quot;Annotatables&quot; that lists out all of the
      requirements elements that are assigned to the issue.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="178.5pt" fileref="0300003E.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Working with Analysis Issues</title>
      </info>

      <para>Every time a requirement element is saved the system’s &quot;Automated
      Assistant&quot; analyses it and adds issues for potential problems or
      improvements. The issues will concern potential spelling errors or
      unfamiliar words, possible glossary terms and actors, complex sentences,
      and poorly structured scenario steps. Issues added during analysis will
      always have the &quot;assistant&quot; user as the creator as shown in the second
      column from the right in Figure 57.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="35.25pt" fileref="0300003F.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The issues added by the assistant have specialized positions that
      automate the task described in the position. Figure 58 shows the
      positions of the issue &quot;The phrase ‘a project’ is a potential glossary
      term, actor, or domain object&quot; from Figure 57. The position &quot;Ignore this
      phrase&quot; resolves the issue without taking any action. The position &quot;Add
      ‘a project’ to the project glossary&quot; adds the term &quot;a project&quot; to the
      glossary and a reference to all the project elements that are assigned
      to the issue, when used to resolve the issue.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="130.5pt" fileref="03000040.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="column-1" colwidth="3438*" />

          <colspec colname="column-2" colwidth="5418*" />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Position Text</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Action taken when the position is used
                  to resolve the issue.</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Add "…" to the project glossary.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Creates the term in the glossary and adds a reference to
                all the project elements that are assigned to the
                issue.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Add "…" as an actor to the project.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Creates a new actor in the project and adds a reference
                to all the project elements that are assigned to the
                issue.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Change the word "…" to "…".</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Updates the name and text of all the requirement
                elements that are assigned to the issue to replace the
                original text with the new text.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Add "…" to the dictionary.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Adds the word to the systems global dictionary so that
                future occurrences of the word will not be identified as
                unknown.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Add the actor &quot;…&quot; to the use case.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Adds the actor to the auxiliary actors of the use
                case.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Change &quot;…&quot; to the primary actor.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Replaces the text in the scenario step with the name of
                the primary actor.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>

        <caption>
          <para>Table 2: Automated Task Positions</para>
        </caption>
      </informaltable>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <info>
      <title>Requel Setup</title>
    </info>

    <para>This section describes the setup of the Requel system. The system is
    distributed as a Java Web Archive File (WAR) and requires only minimal
    configuration to setup.</para>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>System Requirements</title>
      </info>

      <para>Requel is a Web application implemented in the Java language and
      based on the Java Enterprise Edition (JEE5) platform, intended to run in
      a standard Web container. Requel requires the standard Sun Microsystems
      Java runtime version 6 update 4 or later to operate properly. Requel has
      dependencies on Sun’s virtual machine and will not work with a
      third-party virtual machine. Requel is known to work with versions 5.5
      and 6.0 of the Apache Tomcat Web container.</para>

      <para>Requel stores user and project data in a standard SQL database. It
      is known to work with MySQL Server version 5.0. The database
      initialization scripts may have MySQL specific syntax and commands, so
      using a different database my require converting the SQL syntax of the
      files.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Create a Database User</title>
      </info>

      <para>Before Requel can be installed a database user account must be
      created. Requel will use this account to create and initialize the
      database when first installed, and to update the requirements and user
      data during normal operation. It is important that the account has all
      privileges granted for the database that Requel will use.</para>

      <para>The MySQL commands below create a user named ‘requel’ with the
      password ‘password’ and grants all privileges to that user for all
      objects in the database named ‘requeldb’. The database does not need to
      be created ahead of time; Requel will create it on the first startup if
      it doesn’t exist.</para>

      <programlisting>
				CREATE USER 'requel' IDENTIFIED BY 'password'; GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON requeldb.* TO requel; FLUSH
				PRIVILEGES;
			</programlisting>

      <para>Figure 59 shows how to use the MySQL command line interface to
      login as the root user and create the Requel user. If the Web server and
      database server are on different physical servers, then in the create
      user and grant commands append the Web server hostname or IP address to
      the username. For example, requel@192.168.1.100.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="277.5pt" fileref="03000041.png" width="6in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Configuration</title>
      </info>

      <para>The Requel system requires minimal configuration to get running.
      The database settings are the only settings that must be configured
      before the system can be used and they should be configured before
      installing the WAR file in a Web server.</para>

      <para>To configure the database settings the db.properties file must be
      unpacked from the WAR file. This can be done using the Java jar command
      as shown in Figure 60. Create a directory to hold the contents of the
      WAR file and copy the file into that directory. Use the jar command
      below to extract the file:</para>

      <programlisting>
				jar xvf requel.war WEB-INF\classes\db.properties

			</programlisting>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="296.25pt" fileref="03000042.png" width="6in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When the jar command completes there will be a WEB-INF directory.
      Open the file WEB-INF\classes\db.properties in a text editor such as
      WordPad in Windows as shown in Figure 61. You will need to set the
      db.username, db.password, db.server, db.port, and db.name properties.
      Note: the Requel database user must have database creation permission if
      the database specified in the db.name property doesn’t already
      exist.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="152.25pt" fileref="03000043.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After saving the properties file, it must be added back to the WAR
      file. Use the jar command below to add the updated properties file to
      the war file as shown in Figure 62.</para>

      <programlisting>
				jar uvf requel.war WEB-INF\classes\db.properties

			</programlisting>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="100.5pt" fileref="03000044.png" width="6in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The WAR file is now ready to be deployed to a Web server.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Deploying to Apache Tomcat</title>
      </info>

      <para>Apache Tomcat is a freely available open source JEE Web container.
      Use the Web application manger that comes with Tomcat to deploy the
      Requel WAR file. Open a Web browser to the manager page of the Tomcat
      server. The server prompts you for a username and password and then
      displays the manager page as shown in Figure 63.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="225pt" fileref="03000045.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>At the bottom of the page is the WAR file deployment form as shown
      in Figure 64. Use the browse button to locate the Requel WAR file with
      the updated database properties and then click the Deploy button to
      upload and install the application. It will typically take from between
      five and twenty minutes for Requel to create and initialize the database
      depending on the performance of the database server.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="69pt" fileref="03000046.png" width="371.25pt" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When the deployment completes the application manager lists Requel
      in the applications section as shown in Figure 65. Clicking the
      &quot;/requel&quot; link in the &quot;Path&quot; column of the table connects to Requel and
      the login screen should appear as shown in Figure 1. You should record
      the URL from the address bar of the Web browser to send to users for
      accessing the system.</para>

      <figure>
        <info />

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata depth="175.5pt" fileref="03000047.png" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <info>
        <title>Completing the Setup</title>
      </info>

      <para>The first thing to do when the system is ready for access is to
      login using the built-in administrator account and change the password.
      The username and password are both set to ‘admin’ when the system is
      initialized. See the User Administration section for instructions on
      changing the password. You should also change the password of the
      built-in project and assistant users.</para>

      <para>The system is now ready to be used. The next step is creating
      accounts for the users to access the system. See the User Administration
      section for instructions on creating users.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <info>
      <title>User Administration</title>
    </info>

    <para>The primary task of system administrators is creating and managing
    users. System users with the system administrator role are authorized to
    edit user accounts for all users, and to add new users.</para>

    <figure>
      <info />

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="125.25pt" fileref="03000048.png" width="147pt" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>After logging in the left hand side of the screen will contain a tab
    labeled &quot;Users&quot; with a &quot;New User&quot; button for creating new users and tree
    containing all the users of the system as shown in Figure 66. Clicking the
    new user button opens the &quot;New User&quot; editor as shown in Figure 67.
    Clicking on a user name in the tree opens that user for editing. Each user
    must have a username, password, organization, email address, and at least
    one user role. The name and phone number are optional.</para>

    <figure>
      <info />

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="214.5pt" fileref="03000049.png" width="5in" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The user name must be unique. If the chosen name is already in use
    by another user, the system reports an error message to the right of the
    username field as shown in Figure 68.</para>

    <figure>
      <info />

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="27.75pt" fileref="0300004A.png" width="5in" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The user roles and permissions are used to authorize a user to
    access different features of the system. The &quot;Project User Role&quot; grants
    the user access to the project features of the system. The &quot;Create
    Projects&quot; permission under the project user role grants the user the
    ability to create new projects. The &quot;System Admin User Role&quot; grants the
    user access to the user administration function of the system. Figure 69
    shows an example of a user with the project user role and permission to
    create new projects.</para>

    <figure>
      <info />

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata depth="51pt" fileref="0300004B.png" width="5in" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Roles and permissions can be changed after a user is created, but a
    user must always have at least one role. To disable a user’s access to the
    system the password should be reset.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <info>
      <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
    </info>

    <para>Version 1.3, 3 November 2008</para>

    <para>Copyright © 2000, 2001, 2002, 2007, 2008 Free Software Foundation,
    Inc. &lt;http://fsf.org/&gt;</para>

    <para>Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this
    license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>

    <para>0. PREAMBLE</para>

    <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
    functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure
    everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or
    without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily,
    this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit
    for their work, while not being considered responsible for modifications
    made by others.</para>

    <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
    works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It
    complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
    designed for free software.</para>

    <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
    free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
    program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
    software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can
    be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it
    is published as a printed book. We recommend this License principally for
    works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>

    <para>1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</para>

    <para>This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium,
    that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a
    world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work
    under the conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any
    such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is
    addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy, modify or
    distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright
    law.</para>

    <para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the
    Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications
    and/or translated into another language.</para>

    <para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section
    of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the
    publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject
    (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly
    within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook
    of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.) The
    relationship could be a matter of historical connection with the subject
    or with related matters, or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical
    or political position regarding them.</para>

    <para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles
    are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that
    says that the Document is released under this License. If a section does
    not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be
    designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections.
    If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are
    none.</para>

    <para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are
    listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says
    that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may
    be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.</para>

    <para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
    represented in a format whose specification is available to the general
    public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with
    generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint
    programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a
    variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made in
    an otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup,
    has been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by
    readers is not Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for
    any substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
    "Opaque".</para>

    <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
    ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
    XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
    PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent
    image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary
    formats that can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors,
    SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by
    some word processors for output purposes only.</para>

    <para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself,
    plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material
    this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats
    which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near
    the most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning
    of the body of the text.</para>

    <para>The "publisher" means any person or entity that distributes copies
    of the Document to the public.</para>

    <para>A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose
    title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following
    text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands for a
    specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements",
    "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of
    such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
    section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.</para>

    <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
    which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty
    Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
    but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
    these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
    meaning of this License.</para>

    <para>2. VERBATIM COPYING</para>

    <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
    commercially or non-commercially, provided that this License, the
    copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to
    the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
    conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use technical
    measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the
    copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept compensation in
    exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

    <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
    and you may publicly display copies.</para>

    <para>3. COPYING IN QUANTITY</para>

    <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have
    printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
    Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
    copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
    Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
    cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
    publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title
    with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
    other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to
    the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy
    these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
    respects.</para>

    <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
    legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably)
    on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.</para>

    <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering
    more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy
    along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
    computer-network location from which the general network-using public has
    access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete
    Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin
    distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent
    copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
    year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or
    through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

    <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of
    the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
    give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
    Document.</para>

    <para>4. MODIFICATIONS</para>

    <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under
    the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the
    Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version
    filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and
    modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In
    addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

    <para>* A. Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title
    distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous versions
    (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History section of the
    Document). You may use the same title as a previous version if the
    original publisher of that version gives permission.</para>

    <para>* B. List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or
    entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified
    Version, together with at least five of the principal authors of the
    Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless
    they release you from this requirement.</para>

    <para>* C. State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
    Modified Version, as the publisher.</para>

    <para>* D. Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.</para>

    <para>* E. Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
    adjacent to the other copyright notices.</para>

    <para>* F. Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license
    notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under the
    terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.</para>

    <para>* G. Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant
    Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license
    notice.</para>

    <para>* H. Include an unaltered copy of this License.</para>

    <para>* I. Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title,
    and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and
    publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If there is
    no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating the
    title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given on its Title
    Page, then add an item describing the Modified Version as stated in the
    previous sentence.</para>

    <para>* J. Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document
    for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the
    network locations given in the Document for previous versions it was based
    on. These may be placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network
    location for a work that was published at least four years before the
    Document itself, or if the original publisher of the version it refers to
    gives permission.</para>

    <para>* K. For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications",
    Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the
    substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
    dedications given therein.</para>

    <para>* L. Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered
    in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the equivalent are
    not considered part of the section titles.</para>

    <para>* M. Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section may
    not be included in the Modified Version.</para>

    <para>* N. Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
    "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant Section.</para>

    <para>* O. Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</para>

    <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
    appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
    copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all of
    these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of
    Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice. These titles
    must be distinct from any other section titles.</para>

    <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains
    nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various parties—for
    example, statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by
    an organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.</para>

    <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and
    a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list
    of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of Front-Cover
    Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements
    made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for
    the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same
    entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher
    that added the old one.</para>

    <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
    License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert
    or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>

    <para>5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS</para>

    <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
    this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
    versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
    Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list
    them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license
    notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.</para>

    <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
    multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy.
    If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different
    contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end
    of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of
    that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment
    to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license
    notice of the combined work.</para>

    <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History"
    in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History";
    likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any
    sections Entitled "Dedications". You must delete all sections Entitled
    "Endorsements".</para>

    <para>6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</para>

    <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
    documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
    of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
    included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
    License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
    respects.</para>

    <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
    distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy
    of this License into the extracted document, and follow this License in
    all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.</para>

    <para>7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</para>

    <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate
    and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
    distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting
    from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the
    compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit. When the
    Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the
    other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of
    the Document.</para>

    <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
    copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the
    entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that
    bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of
    covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear
    on printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.</para>

    <para>8. TRANSLATION</para>

    <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
    Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission
    from their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or
    all Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these
    Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this License, and all
    the license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers,
    provided that you also include the original English version of this
    License and the original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In
    case of a disagreement between the translation and the original version of
    this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will
    prevail.</para>

    <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
    "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
    Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual title.</para>

    <para>9. TERMINATION</para>

    <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document
    except as expressly provided under this License. Any attempt otherwise to
    copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute it is void, and will automatically
    terminate your rights under this License.</para>

    <para>However, if you cease all violation of this License, then your
    license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated (a)
    provisionally, unless and until the copyright holder explicitly and
    finally terminates your license, and (b) permanently, if the copyright
    holder fails to notify you of the violation by some reasonable means prior
    to 60 days after the cessation.</para>

    <para>Moreover, your license from a particular copyright holder is
    reinstated permanently if the copyright holder notifies you of the
    violation by some reasonable means, this is the first time you have
    received notice of violation of this License (for any work) from that
    copyright holder, and you cure the violation prior to 30 days after your
    receipt of the notice.</para>

    <para>Termination of your rights under this section does not terminate the
    licenses of parties who have received copies or rights from you under this
    License. If your rights have been terminated and not permanently
    reinstated, receipt of a copy of some or all of the same material does not
    give you any rights to use it.</para>

    <para>10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</para>

    <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
    the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
    will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail
    to address new problems or concerns. See
    http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.</para>

    <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
    number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
    this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of
    following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of
    any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free
    Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of
    this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft)
    by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document specifies that a proxy
    can decide which future versions of this License can be used, that proxy's
    public statement of acceptance of a version permanently authorizes you to
    choose that version for the Document.</para>

    <para>11. RELICENSING</para>

    <para>"Massive Multiauthor Collaboration Site" (or "MMC Site") means any
    World Wide Web server that publishes copyrightable works and also provides
    prominent facilities for anybody to edit those works. A public wiki that
    anybody can edit is an example of such a server. A "Massive Multiauthor
    Collaboration" (or "MMC") contained in the site means any set of
    copyrightable works thus published on the MMC site.</para>

    <para>"CC-BY-SA" means the Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0
    license published by Creative Commons Corporation, a not-for-profit
    corporation with a principal place of business in San Francisco,
    California, as well as future copyleft versions of that license published
    by that same organization.</para>

    <para>"Incorporate" means to publish or republish a Document, in whole or
    in part, as part of another Document.</para>

    <para>An MMC is "eligible for relicensing" if it is licensed under this
    License, and if all works that were first published under this License
    somewhere other than this MMC, and subsequently incorporated in whole or
    in part into the MMC, (1) had no cover texts or invariant sections, and
    (2) were thus incorporated prior to November 1, 2008.</para>

    <para>The operator of an MMC Site may republish an MMC contained in the
    site under CC-BY-SA on the same site at any time before August 1, 2009,
    provided the MMC is eligible for relicensing.</para>

    <para>ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents</para>

    <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy
    of the License in the document and put the following copyright and license
    notices just after the title page:</para>

    <para>Copyright (C) YEAR YOUR NAME.</para>

    <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
    document</para>

    <para>under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
    1.3</para>

    <para>or any later version published by the Free Software
    Foundation;</para>

    <para>with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
    Texts.</para>

    <para>A copy of the license is included in the section entitled
    "GNU</para>

    <para>Free Documentation License".</para>

    <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
    Texts, replace the "with … Texts." line with this:</para>

    <para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the</para>

    <para>Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being
    LIST.</para>

    <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
    combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
    situation.</para>

    <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
    recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
    software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their
    use in free software.</para>
  </chapter>