<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Requel - the Collaborative Requirments Elicitation System.
  ~
  ~ Copyright © 2008, 2009 Ron Regan Jr.
  ~
  ~ Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
  ~ under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
  ~ any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
  ~ Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts and no Back-Cover Texts.  
  ~ See <http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html>
  ~   
-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY gettingstarted SYSTEM "GettingStarted.xml" NDATA SGML>
]>
    <sect1 id="Chp_WorkingWithRequirements_Sec_CreatingAProject">
        <title>Creating a Project</title>

      <para>Requel organizes requirements into projects. If you have project
      creation authorization the &quot;New Project&quot; button appears at the top of
      the project navigation tab as shown in <olink targetdoc="gettingstarted" targetptr="Fig_ProjectNavigationTab"/>. Clicking the button
      opens the &quot;New Project&quot; screen show in <xref linkend="Fig_ProjectNewForm"/>. Enter a name,
      organization, optional description, and click the save button. The
      combination of project name and organization are required to be unique.
      The system verifies the values are valid, creates the project, and adds
      it to the project navigation tab. If there are validation problems the
      system puts a message to the right of the affected fields.</para>

    <figure id="Fig_ProjectNewForm" float="1">
	  <title>New Project Form</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/ProjectNew.PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

      <para>Requel also supports importing a project stored in an XML file. If
      you have project creation authorization the &quot;Import Project&quot; button
      appears below the &quot;New Project&quot; button in the project navigation tab as
      shown in <olink targetdoc="gettingstarted" targetptr="Fig_ProjectNavigationTab"/>. 
      The button opens the &quot;Import Project&quot; screen show in <xref linkend="Fig_ProjectImportForm"/>.</para>

    <figure id="Fig_ProjectImportForm" float="1">
	  <title>Import Project Form</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/ProjectImport.PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

      <para>To import a project from an XML file, click the &quot;Browse&quot; button in
      the &quot;Upload&quot; field and use the file upload dialog to navigate to the
      file to import as shown in <xref linkend="Fig_ProjectImportFileSelection"/>.
      If you are importing a project that
      already exists in Requel, you must change the name by entering a new
      name in the &quot;Rename&quot; field to meet the uniqueness requirement described
      earlier.</para>

    <figure id="Fig_ProjectImportFileSelection" float="1">
	  <title>Import Project Form</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/ProjectImportFileUpload.PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

      <para>When importing a project you have the option to turn off analysis
      by unchecking the &quot;Enable Analysis&quot; checkbox. This is useful for
      projects that were exported from the system and the elements have
      already been analyzed. Since the analysis uses a significant amount of
      processing power and can take a long time to complete. Projects created
      by hand or by another tool in the project XML format should have
      analysis enabled.</para>

      <para>After selecting the file in the upload dialog, click the &quot;Upload&quot;
      button to upload the project file to the server. Then click the &quot;Save&quot;
      button at the bottom of the screen. The system creates a new project and
      adds it to the project navigation tab.</para>
    </sect1>
