<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Requel - the Collaborative Requirments Elicitation System.
  ~
  ~ Copyright © 2008, 2009 Ron Regan Jr.
  ~
  ~ Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
  ~ under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
  ~ any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
  ~ Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts and no Back-Cover Texts.  
  ~ See <http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html>
  ~   
-->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
   <title>Acknowledgements and Disclaimers</title>

    <para>Requel uses many open source components and data. Apache Xalan and
    Xerces for XML processing; Apache Commons libraries; Proxool Java
    connection pool; the MySQL connector for Java; the Spring Framework;
    Hibernate Java Persistence; the Stanford Parser; the Stanford Named Entity
    Recognizer; Jazzy spell checker; OpenNLP Tools; GNU Trove; WordNet SQL
    builder; WordNet; VerbNet; Extended WordNet; Echo2 Web Framework;
    EchoPointNG;</para>

    <para>This product includes software developed by the Apache Software
    Foundation (http://www.apache.org/).</para>

    <para>This product includes software developed by the Proxool Project
    (http://proxool.sourceforge.net/).</para>

    <para>This product includes software developed by Spring Framework Project
    (http://www.springframework.org).</para>

    <para>Hibernate is licensed under the GNU LGPL, Copyright by Red Hat
    Middleware LLC (http://www.hibernate.org).</para>

    <para>GNU Trove is licensed under the GNU LGPL, Copyright 2001 Eric D.
    Friedman and portions Copyright 1999 CERN - European Organization for
    Nuclear Research (http://trove4j.sourceforge.net/).</para>

    <para>Jazzy is licensed under the GNU LGPL, Copyright 2001 Mindaugas
    Idzelis. (http://jazzy.sourceforge.net/).</para>

    <para>OpenNLP Tools are licensed under the GNU LGPL, Copyright 2004 Jason
    Baldridge, Gann Bierner and Tom Morton.
    (http://opennlp.sourceforge.net/).</para>

    <para>The Stanford Parser is licensed under the GNU GPL, Copyright 2002,
    2003, 2004, 2005 The Board of Trustees of The Leland Stanford Junior
    University. (http://nlp.stanford.edu/software/lex-parser.shtml).</para>

    <para>The Stanford Named Entity Recognizer is licensed under the GNU GPL,
    Copyright 2002-2006 The Board of Trustees of The Leland Stanford Junior
    University. (http://nlp.stanford.edu/ner/index.shtml).</para>

    <para>WordNet SQL builder is licensed under the GNU LGPL, Copyright 2009
    <emphasis role="bold">Bernard Bou. (</emphasis>
    http://wnsqlbuilder.sourceforge.net/ <emphasis
    role="bold">).</emphasis></para>

    <para>Echo2 Web Framework is licensed under the Mozilla Public License,
    GNU LGPL, or the GNU GPL, Copyright 2009 NextApp, Inc.
    (http://echo.nextapp.com/site/echo2).</para>

    <para>EchoPointNG is licensed under Public License, GNU LGPL, or the GNU
    LGPL, Copyright 2009 bbakerman.
    (http://echo.nextapp.com/site/echo2).</para>

    <para>WordNet Release 3.0 License (http://wordnet.princeton.edu/)</para>

    <para>This software and database is being provided to you, the LICENSEE,
    by Princeton University under the following license. By obtaining, using,
    and/or copying this software and database, you agree that you have read,
    understood, and will comply with these terms and conditions:</para>

    <para>Permission to use, copy, modify, and distribute this software and
    database and its documentation for any purpose and without fee or royalty
    is hereby granted, provided that you agree to comply with the following
    copyright notice and statements, including the disclaimer, and that the
    same appear on ALL copies of the software, database and documentation,
    including modifications that you make for internal use or for
    distribution.</para>

    <para>WordNet 3.0 Copyright 2006 by Princeton University. All rights
    reserved.</para>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE AND DATABASE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND PRINCETON
    UNIVERSITY MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED. BY
    WAY OF EXAMPLE, BUT NOT LIMITATION, PRINCETON UNIVERSITY MAKES NO
    REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES OF MERCHANT- ABILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY
    PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR THAT THE USE OF THE LICENSED SOFTWARE, DATABASE OR
    DOCUMENTATION WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY THIRD PARTY PATENTS, COPYRIGHTS,
    TRADEMARKS OR OTHER RIGHTS.</para>

    <para>The name of Princeton University or Princeton may not be used in
    advertising or publicity pertaining to distribution of the software and/or
    database. Title to copyright in this software, database and any associated
    documentation shall at all times remain with Princeton University and
    LICENSEE agrees to preserve same.</para>

    <para>VerbNet 2.1 License
    (http://verbs.colorado.edu/~mpalmer/projects/verbnet.html)</para>

    <para>This software and database is being provided to you, the LICENSEE,
    by University of Colorado under the following license. By obtaining, using
    and/or copying this software and database, you agree that you have read,
    understood, and will comply with these terms and conditions:</para>

    <para>Permission to use, copy, modify and distribute this software and
    database and its documentation for any purpose and without fee or royalty
    is hereby granted, provided that you agree to comply with the following
    copyright notice and statements, including the disclaimer, and that the
    same appear on ALL copies of the software, database and documentation,
    including modifications that you make for internal use or for
    distribution.</para>

    <para>VerbNet 2.1 Copyright 2006 by University of Colorado. All rights
    reserved.</para>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE AND DATABASE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND UNIVERSITY OF
    COLORADO MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED. BY
    WAY OF EXAMPLE, BUT NOT LIMITATION, UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO MAKES NO
    REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES OF MERCHANT-ABILITY OR FITNESS FOR ANY
    PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR THAT THE USE OF THE LICENSED SOFTWARE, DATABASE OR
    DOCUMENTATION WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY THIRD PARTY PATENTS, COPYRIGHTS,
    TRADEMARKS OR OTHER RIGHTS.</para>

    <para>The name of University of Colorado or CU may not be used in
    advertising or publicity pertaining to distribution of the software and/or
    database. Title to copyright in this software, database and any associated
    documentation shall at all times remain with University of Colorado and
    LICENSEE agrees to preserve same.</para>

    <para>Extended WordNet License (http://xwn.hlt.utdallas.edu/)</para>

    <para>XWN 2.0-1.1 software and database is being provided to you, the
    LICENSEE, by the University of Texas at Dallas under the following
    license. By obtaining, using and/or copying this software and database,
    you agree that you have read, understood, and will comply with these terms
    and conditions:</para>

    <para>Permission to use, copy, modify and distribute this software and
    database and its documentation for any purpose and without fee or royalty
    is hereby granted, provided that you agree to comply with the following
    copyright notice and statements, including the disclaimer, and that the
    same appear on ALL copies of the software, database and documentation,
    including modifications that you make for internal use or for
    distribution.</para>

    <para>eXtended WordNet 2.0-1.1 for WordNet 2.0 Copyright © 2003 by the
    University of Texas at Dallas. All rights reserved. (WordNet is
    copyrighted by the Princeton University)</para>

    <para>THIS SOFTWARE AND DATABASE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE UNIVERSITY OF
    TEXAS AT DALLAS MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED. BY WAY OF EXAMPLE, BUT NOT LIMITATION, UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT
    DALLAS MAKES NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR
    FITNESS FOR ANY PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR THAT THE USE OF THE LICENSED
    SOFTWARE, DATABASE OR DOCUMENTATION WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY THIRD PARTY
    PATENTS, COPYRIGHTS, TRADEMARKS OR OTHER RIGHTS.</para>

    <para>The name of University of Texas at Dallas may not be used in
    advertising or publicity pertaining to distribution of the software and/or
    database. Title to copyright in this software, database and any associated
    documentation shall at all times remain with University of Texas at Dallas
    and LICENSEE agrees to preserve same.</para>
  </chapter>
